Personal information



Spanish 07/09/1991

Darías Holgado

Researcher

Institute of sport sciences, University of Lausanne,

Quartier UNIL Centre, Bâtiment Synathlon,

CH-1010 Lausanne

darias.holgado@unil.ch

Brief summary

My research line is transdisciplinary since I have worked on exercise science under the focus of experimental Psychology and neuroscience. I consider of paramount importance a policy for the Open Science to improve the credibility of science (e.g., preregistration of studies, data sharing) and doing meta research. I consider myself as highly motivated and productive to develop the competencies of my position.

Keywords: mental fatigue; meta science; experimental psychology; exercise performance; brain stimulation; cognition

Employment

01/2022 - Present	Researcher at Institute of Sport Science, University of Lausanne, Switzerland and Mind, Brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada, Spain			
10/2019 – 04/2020	Postdoc at the Mind, Brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada, Spain			
10/2015 – 09/2019	PhD Student at the Department of Physical Education & Sport and Mind, Brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada, Spain			
09/2018 – 12/2018	PhD. Internship in Campus Biotech. University of Geneva, Switzerland.			
04/2014 – 10/2015	Research fellow at the Department of Physical Education & Sport, University of Granada, Spain			
09/2013 – 08/2014	Research assistant at the Department of Physical Education & Sport, University of Granada, Spain			

Education

September 2019 International PhD in Biomedicine. University of Granada

Thesis tittle: "Executive functions, self-paced exercise and cycling

performance". Advisors: Daniel Sanabria and Mikel Zabala

October 2015 Master of Research in sport and physical Activity. University of

Granada

July 2014 BSc. in Sport Sciences (Extraordinary Degree Award). University of

Granada

Publications

 Luis F. Ciria, Rafael Román-Caballero, Miguel Vadillo, Darías Holgado, Antonio Luque-Casado, Pandelis Perakakis & Daniel Sanabria. (2023). An umbrella review of randomized control trials on the effects of physical exercise on cognition. *Nature Human Behavior*. https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01554-4

- 2. **Darías Holgado**, Léo Jolidon, Guillermo Borragan, Daniel Sanabria, Nicolas Place. (2023). Individualized mental fatigue does not impact neuromuscular function and exercise performance. *Medicine and Science in Sport and Exercise*. https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/Fulltext/9900/Individualized Mental Fatigue Does Not Impact.292.aspx
- 3. **Darias Holgado**, Christian Mesquida, Rafael Román-Caballero Assessing the evidential value mental fatigue and exercise research. (2023). SportrXiv: https://doi.org/10.51224/SRXIV.245
- 4. **Darías Holgado** & Thomas Zandonai. (2022) Comment on "What is the Effect of Paracetamol (Acetaminophen) Ingestion on Exercise Performance? Current Findings and Future Research Directions." Sports Med. 2022;52:2561–2.
- 5. Thomas Zandonai, **Darías Holgado**, Luis F. Ciria, James Hopker, Mikel Zabala, Tristan Bekinschtein, & Daniel Sanabria Sanabria, D. (2021). Novel evidence on the effect of tramadol on self-paced high-intensity cycling. Journal of Sport Science. Doi: 10.1080/02640414.2021.1877440
- 6. **Darías Holgado**; Daniel Sanabria; José C. Perales and Miguel A. Vadillo. (2020). "Mental fatigue might be not so bad for exercise performance after all: A Systematic Review and Bias-sensitive Meta-analysis." Journal of Cognition. https://doi.org/10.5334/joc.126.
- 7. **Darias Holgado** & Daniel Sanabria. (2020). "Does self-paced exercise depend on executive processing? A narrative review of the current evidence." International Review of Sport and Exercise Psychology. doi: https://doi.org/10.1080/1750984X.2020.1774915
- 8. **Darías Holgado**; Esther Troya; José C. Perales; Miguel A. Vadillo and Daniel Sanabria. (2020). "Does mental fatigue impair physical performance? A replication study" European Journal of Sport Science. https://doi.org/10.1080/17461391.2020.1781265.
- 9. Thomas Zandonai & **Darias Holgado.** (2020). Doping in tennis, where we are and where we should be going? Performance Enhancement & Health. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.peh.2020.100157
- 10. Darías Holgado (2019). Executive Functions, Self-Paced Exercise and Cycling Performance [Doctoral dissertation, University of Granada, Spain]. Supervisor: Daniel Sanabria and Mikel Zabala. *Thesis Common*. 10.31237/osf.io/vtyfu.

- 11. **Darías Holgado**; Miguel A. Vadillo; Daniel Sanabria. (2019). 'Brain-doping ', is it a real threat? **Frontiers in Physiology.** https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2019.00483
- 12. **Darías Holgado**.; Mikel Zabala; Daniel Sanabria. (2019). No evidence of the effect of cognitive load on self-paced cycling performance. Plos One. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0217825
- 13. **Darías Holgado**; Thomas Zandonai; Luis F Ciria; Mikel Zabala; James Hopker; Daniel Sanabria. (2019). Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) over the left prefrontal cortex does not affect time-trial self-paced cycling performance: Evidence from oscillatory brain activity and power output. Plos One. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210873
- 14. Darías Holgado; Thomas Zandonai; Daniel Sanabria. (2019). Comment on "Review of WADA Prohibited Substances: Limited Evidence for Performance-Enhancing Effects". Sports Medicine. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40279-019-01062-4
- 15. **Darías Holgado**; Miguel A. Vadillo; Daniel Sanabria. (2018). The effects of transcranial direct current stimulation on objective and subjective measures of sports performance: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Brain Stimulation. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brs.2018.12.002.
- 16. Ana Peinado; Darías Holgado; Antonio Luque Casado; Miguel Rojo Tirado; Daniel Sanabria Lucena; Coral González; Manuel Mateo-March; Cristobal Sanchez Muñoz; Francisco Calderón; Mikel Zabala. 2018. Effect of induced alkalosis on performance during a field-simulated BMX cycling competition. Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport. 08/2018. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsams.2018.08.010
- 17. **Darías Holgado**; Thomas Zandonai; Mikel Zabala; James Hopker; Pandelis Perakakis; Antonio Luque Casado; Luis Ciria; Eduardo Guerra Hernandez; Daniel Sanabria. 2017. Tramadol effects on physical performance and sustained attention during a 20-min indoor cycling time-trial: A randomised controlled trial. Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport. 01/11/2017. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsams.2017.10.032
- Luis F Ciria; Antonio Luque-Casado; Daniel Sanabria; Darías Holgado; Plamen Ch Ivanov; Pandelis Perakakis. 2018. Oscillatory brain activity during acute exercise: Tonic and transient neural response to an Oddball task. Psychophysiology. 10.1111/psyp.13326
- 19. **Darías Holgado**; James Hopker; Daniel Sanabria; Mikel Zabala. 2017. Analgesics and Sport Performance: Beyond the Pain Modulating Effects. PM&R. 10.1016/j.pmrj.2017.07.068

C.1.2 Ongoing projects

- 20. Hard physical exercise might be bad for your mind. https://osf.io/cz3s5/
- 21. Can we actually enhance exercise performance by stimulating the brain? Evidence from an umbrella review. https://osf.io/73qsu/.

Funding

- 1 Participating member: Putting the brain at work: Self-regulated acute aerobic exercise and executive control. Spanish Ministerio de Economía y Hacienda. Pi: Daniel Sanabria. (University of Granada) 01/01/2017-31/12/2019. 54.500 €.
- 2 Participating member: Clinical trial on the effects of the combination of tramadol and paracetamol on physical, cognitive and brain performance during cycling. World Anti-Doping Agency (WADA). Pi: Daniel Sanabria. (University of Granada). 01/07/2018-01/07/2020. 94.556,01 €.

3 Participating member: Tramadol and sport: Effects on physical and sustained attention performance during cycling exercise. World Anti-Doping Agency (WADA). Pi: Daniel Sanabria. (University of Granada). 15/02/2016-15/02/2016. 67.000 €.

Teaching

- Course: Behavioral analysis and motor development. Degree: BSc. Sport Sciences.
 Academic Year: 2022/2023 Credits ECTS: 3 Faculty: Sport Sciences. University of Granada
- Course: Are we moving sport sciences forward? The need for effective and transparent practices. Master seminar. Academic Year: 2022. Faculty: Institute of Sport Science, University of Lausanne, Switzerland.
- Course: Fundamentals of Sport IV: Cycling. Degree: BSc. Sport Sciences. Academic Year: 2017/2018, 2018/2019. Credits ECTS: 6 Faculty: Sport Sciences. University of Granada
- Course: Sport Specialization: Cycling. Degree: BSc. Sport Sciences. Academic Year: 2016/2017, 2018/2019. Credits ECTS: 6 Faculty: Sport Sciences. University of Granada
- Course: Sport Advanced Course: Cycling. Degree: BSc. Sport Sciences. Academic Year: 2017/2018. Credits ECTS: 3. Faculty: Sport Sciences. University of Granada

Additional formation

Languages

Language	Listening	Reading	Speaking	Writing
French	C1	C1	B2	B2
German (Hochdeutsch)	B2	B2	B1-B2	B1
Italian	C1	C1	B2	B2
English	C1	C1	C1	C1

Self-reported level

Relevant courses

- MATLAB programming. 20h. University of Granada.
- Data Science in R. Basics Course; Inference and Modeling; Probability; Visualization. 60h. edX (Harvard).
- Advanced design and multivariate analysis. 20h. University of Granada.
- EEG/ERPs data analysis with EEGLAB-ERPLAB MATLAB tool. 10h. Mind, brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada.
- EEG/ERPs data analysis with Fieldtrip, MATLAB. 15h. Mind, brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada.
- Methodology in Psychology: preparing experimental studies with E-prime. 15h. Mind, Brain and Behavior Research Centre, University of Granada.